Guide to the American Library Association, International Relations Committee Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
American Library Association, International Relations Committee Records
1941-1967.
American Library Association. International Relations Committee.
13 linear ft (ca. 9.000 items in 25 boxes and 1 scrapbook).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4078578
History
The Committee's aim to foster exchange of ideas and methods between American and foreign librarians is reflected in its programs of visits by librarians both to and from the United States, technical assistance of American librarians acting as consultants to librarians in the developing nations of Asia and Latin America, and participation in international library organizations: International Federation of Library Associations, Féderation Internationale de Documentation, and UNESCO.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, agenda, and related printed matter concerning the programs of the American Library Association's (ALA) International Relations Committee, 1941-1967. These were the working files of Jack Dalton who was Director of ALA's International Relations Office, 1956-1959. The internal office files of the Board and Committee are also included.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: IRB
Series II: IRC
Series III: Flora B. Ludington
Subjects
International Federation of Library Associations.; International Federation for Documentation.; American Library Association.--International Relations Office.; Unesco.; Dalton, Jack, 1908-; Librarians--Asia.; Librarians--Latin America.; Library science--Societies, etc.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1976 M71-03-17 Dalton, Jack Gift
Gift of Jack Dalton, 1970 & 1979; Gift of the School of Librtary Service, 1976.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I. IRB Series
  - ALA. Executive Board--Minutes, 1954-56 (Box 1)
  - Budget--Correspondence, 1952-56 (Box 1)
  - Committee on International Cultural Relations--Minutes and Reports, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Congressional Committee (Cox)--Correspondence and Clippings, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Congressional Committee (Hickenlooper)--Correspondence and Clippings, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942-44, 1952-54 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1955-56 (Box 2)
  - IFLA
    - Correspondence, 1952-56 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1955-60 (Box 2)
  - International Organization for Standards
    - ISO/TC 46 (Box 2)
    - ISO/TC 46/SC1 (Box 2)
    - ISO/TC 46/SCl, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - ISO/TC 37/S2-S4 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1942-1956 (Box 3)
  - Memoranda, Correspondence, 1941-1956 (Box 3)
  - Pan American Union--Reports, 1952-1957 (Box 3)
  - Project
    - Afghanistan--Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - Asia, Committee for Free--Correspondence, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Australian Resolution--Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Caribbean Committee--Library
      - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
      - Meeting--Correspondence, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Children Services--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Cuban Library Association--Correspondence, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Distribution. Commager--Correspondence, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Exchange
      - American--Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 4)
      - Federation Int. de Documentation. Manual on Re-Presentation, 1952 (Box 4)
      - Foreign--Correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 4)
      - German
        - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 4)
        - Questionnaire, 1954 (Box 4)
        - Tour--Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
      - Materials--Correspondence and Reports, 1952-1956 (Box 4)
      - Russian-American--Correspondence, 1955 (Box 4)
    - India--Visit--Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
    - Indonesian Library Service--Report on Survey, 1953 (Box 4)
    - International Congress--Correspondence, 1952 (Box 5)
    - Japanese Library School--Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 5)
    - Latin-American Libraries--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - Munich Youth Library--Correspondence, 1952-1960 (Box 5)
    - Overseas Library Development--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1956-1958 (Box 5)
    - Paris-American Libraries--Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
    - Russian Libraries--Reports, 1928, 1936 (Box 5)
    - South Pacific Committee--Proposal, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Specialist Program, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Translation
      - German--Correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 5)
      - Japanese--Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 5)
      - Policy--Correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 5)
      - Portuguese--Correspondence, 1952-1956 (Box 6)
      - Spanish--Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 6)
      - Turkish--Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 6)
      - Visit. Foreign--Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 6)
  - Reports, 1942-1957 (Box 6)
  - State Department--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1943-1944 (Box 6)
  - UNESCO--Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 6)
  - US Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange, 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - USIS
    - General, 1953-1956 (Box 6)
    - Book Selection. 1953-1956 (Box 6)
- Series II. IRC Series
  - Agenda of Meetings, 1957-1965 (Box 7)
  - American Library Association (ALA)
    - IRC--General (3 Folders) (Box 22)
    - Council (Box 22)
    - Current Committee (Box 22)
    - Special Presidential Program (Box 23)
  - Budget, 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - Chairman--Memoranda, 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - Congressional Committee
    - Exchange of Persons--Correspondence and Reports, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Information Media--Correspondence and Reports, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - 1957-1960 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 8)
  - Diplomas Awarded to Foreign Librarians for Training Institutes (Box 9)
  - Exchange Program (Box 23)
  - Federation Internationale de Documentation. (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and Reports, 1958-1963 (Box 9)
    - Inventory--Memoranda, 1961-1965 (Box 9)
    - Reports, 1956-1960 (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 23)
  - Foreign Area Fellowship Program (Box 23)
  - India, 1957-60 (Box 9)
  - IFLA
    - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 9)
    - Minutes, 1954-1960 (Box 9)
  - International Education (Box 23)
  - International Relations Committee
    - General (3 Folders) (Box 23)
    - Joint Committee on Library Education (Box 23)
  - International Relations Office
    - Correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box 9)
    - Diaries of Trips
      - 1961-1962 (Box 9)
      - 1962-1967 (Box 10)
    - Director’s Office--Diary and Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
    - Proposals, Grants, 1958-1961 (Box 10)
    - Reports, 1958-1964 (Box 10)
    - Travel Reports
      - General
        - (5 Folders) (Box 23)
        - (5 Folders) (Box 24)
      - Bryant, Douglas (Box 24)
      - Cunningham, Eileen (Box 24)
      - Dalton, Jack, (4 Folders) (Box 25)
      - Fukuda, Naomi (Box 25)
      - Scott, Dorothea (Box 25)
      - Snead, Clarice R. (Box 25)
  - International Relations Round Table
    - Correspondence, Reports, and Minutes, 1957-1962 (Box 11)
    - Releases, 1957-1958 (Box 11)
  - Minutes, 1959-1965 (Box 11)
  - Organization and Policy--Correspondence, 1956-1965 (Box 11)
  - Project
    - Africa--Correspondence, 1957-1961 (Box 11)
    - Arab States. Seminar--Correspondence and Reports, 1959-1965 (Box 11)
    - Asia--Correspondence and Reports, 1957-1960 (Box 11)
    - Bulgaria (See Poland) (Box 12)
    - Burma--Correspondence and Reports, 1956-1961 (Box 12)
    - Ceylon--Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 12)
    - Children's Services, 1957-1960 (Box 12)
    - China--Hong Kong--Correspondence and Reports, 1959 (Box 12)
    - Czechoslovakia (See Poland) (Box 12)
    - Egypt--Correspondence and Reports, 1956-1961 (Box 12)
    - Exchange
      - American--Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 12)
      - Foreign--Correspondence, 1956-1960 (Box 12)
      - Italian
        - General, 1957 (Box 12)
          (See Also - Scrapbook at end of the series)
        - Questionnaires, 1956 (Box 13)
      - Japanese--Correspondence, 1957-1961 (Box 13)
      - Materials--Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 13)
      - Russian-American--Correspondence
        - 1957-1960 (Box 13)
        - 1961 (Box 14)
    - Hawaii--Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 14)
    - Hungarian Refugees--Correspondence, 1957 (Box 14)
    - India
      - Institute of Library Service--Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 14)
      - Visit
        - Correspondence, Memoranda, and Reports
          - 1956-1960 (Box 14)
          - 1961-1962 (Box 15)
    - International Seminar. Agenda--Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 15)
    - Iran--Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 15)
    - Iraq--Bagdad--Correspondence, 1961 (Box 15)
    - Japan--Field Seminar--Correspondence and Reports, 1957-1960 (Box 15)
    - Joint Foreign Librarians Program--Correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 15)
    - Korea--Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 16)
    - Latin America--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
    - Mexico--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
    - Middle East--Correspondence, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Multi-national Group Librarians Project, 1961-1962 (Box 16)
    - Pakistan--Correspondence, 1959 (Box 16)
    - Philippines--Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 16)
    - Poland, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, 1958-1961 (Box 16)
    - Russian Librarianship, 1958 (Box 16)
    - Specialist Programs--Correspondence and Reports, 1940-1964 (Box 17)
    - Taiwan--Correspondence and Memoranda, 1961 (Box 17)
    - Turkey, Library Institute--Correspondence and Reports, 1956-1961 (Box 17)
  - Russia--Correspondence and Reports, 1957-1959 (Box 17)
  - Study Tour--Correspondence, 1963 (Box 18)
  - UNESCO.
    - Correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 18)
    - Organization & Policy--Memoranda, 1958-1960 (Box 18)
    - Panel--Memoranda, 1958-1964 (Box 18)
    - Postal Convention--Correspondence, 1957 (Box 18)
  - U. S. Book Exchange--Correspondence and Reports, 1952-1957 (Box 19)
  - USIS--Correspondence and Reports, 1957-1964 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook--Program of Educational Exchange for Librarians from Italy, 1956 (Box Flat Box 2)
- Series III. Flora B. Ludington Series
  - Allied Ministers of Education (Box 20)
  - Assembly of Librarians of the Americas (Box 20)
  - Book Campaign (Box 20)
  - British Post-War Plans (Box 20)
  - Children's Library Association (Box 20)
  - Coney Field Totes (Box 20)
  - Foreign Library Service(Melinat Report) (Box 20)
  - International Education (Box 20)
  - International Relations Board
    - Miscellaneous Reports, 1947-1949 (Box 20)
    - Transitions (Box 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 20)
  - International Relations Committee (Box 20)
  - Latin America, Books for (Box 21)
  - Library Cooperation with China and the Orient (Box 21)
  - Library Cooperation with Europe and Africa (Box 21)
  - Lord, Wilton (Box 21)
  - Lyndenberg, Harry Miller (Box 21)
  - Mekinsky, A. (Box 21)
  - Metcalf, Keyes (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 21)
  - Russell, John R. (Box 21)
  - Sao Paulo Library School (Box 21)
  - State Department (Box 21)